<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of M. Anthony Hinton late treasurer of St. Bartholomews Hospital on the 15th of November, 1678, at St. Sepulchres Church / by William Bell.</title>
            <author>Bell, William, 1626-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1811</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24054</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07944533</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07944533</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40625</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27360)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40625)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1195:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of M. Anthony Hinton late treasurer of St. Bartholomews Hospital on the 15th of November, 1678, at St. Sepulchres Church / by William Bell.</title>
                  <author>Bell, William, 1626-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Clark,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hinton, Anthony, d. 1678.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40625:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40625:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL OF M. <hi>ANTHONY HINTON:</hi> Late Treaſurer of St. <hi>Bartholomews</hi> Hoſpital.</p>
            <p>On the 15th. of <hi>November,</hi> 1678. At St. <hi>Sepulchres</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>BY WILLIAM BELL, D.D. and Vicar of the ſaid Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Clark,</hi> and to be ſold by <hi>Benj. Tooke</hi> at the Ship in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40625:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40625:2"/>
            <head>To my ever honoured Friend, Mrs. <hi>MARY HINTON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> have herein what you earneſtly deſired, and have truly deſerved of me, the Sermon preached at the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of your deceaſed, and juſtly beloved Husband; and now at the inſtance of his near Friends, made more publick: and their deſires had been ſooner complied with, but that it pleaſed God by a fit of ſickneſs to hinder me, and thereby it, from coming ſooner abroad. His life was a better Comment on the Text, than any I could make. He was ſuch an Original, as did (as Originals uſually do) exceed the Copy; ſo that I lay claim herein not to your thanks, but to your pardon: And for
<pb facs="tcp:40625:3"/>that too I have no other plea, but that you commanded me to ſhew my weakneſs. But though I fell ſhort in the Application, I may fear I have exceeded in the Diſcourſe it ſelf, having added much that was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, but could not be then delivered, by reaſon of the ſtraitneſs of time allowed to ſuch occaſions. That you may receive ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual advantage, and comfort by all, you have, together with the Sermon, the hearty conſtant Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>St. <hi>Sepulchres,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 28. 1678/9.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your faithful Servant in our common Maſter, Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>William Bell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40625:3"/>
            <head>A Funeral Sermon, ON</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ACTS xxiv. 16.</bibl>
                  <p>Herein do I exerciſe my ſelf, to have always a Conſcience void of offence toward God, and toward Men.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Chapter of the Text is the Account of a Trial,
<note place="margin">Ver. 1.</note> wherein the Judge is <hi>Felix;</hi> the Plaintiffs are the <hi>Jews,</hi> and their <hi>High Prieſts;</hi> and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullus,</hi> of Council for them; the Defendant is St. <hi>Paul;</hi> the Crimes laid to his charge are Sedition, Schiſm, and <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> which, if true, rendred him undeſerving of life, and liberty, who yet by his very enemies was judged to <hi>have done nothing worthy of Death, or of Bonds.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts xxiii. 29.</note> He eaſily wipes off theſe aſperſions by the evidence of his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40625:4"/>peaceable behaviour <hi>in the Synagogue,</hi> and <hi>in the City;</hi> All his guilt was <hi>honouring the Father in honouring the Son,</hi> which was the old Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> though by the modern <hi>Jews</hi> condemned of Novelty,
<note place="margin">Ver. 14. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text.</note> and <hi>Hereſie:</hi> And aſſerting the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was an <hi>Article</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> as well as <hi>Chriſtian Creed;</hi> which <hi>Reſurrection</hi> becauſe it was to be <hi>both of the Juſt and the Unjuſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 15. to 21.</note> all his deſign and endeavour was to make that ſafe, which was already ſure; that <hi>if by any means he might attain the reſurrection to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. xii. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>and not to ſhame and everlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt;</hi> and in purſuance of that end, he did <hi>exerciſe himſelf to have a Conſcience void of offence toward God and toward Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not ſuſpect your knowledge of the Hiſtory of this our Apoſtles life, ſo as to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the proof of the truth of the Aſſertion in his perſon,
<note place="margin">Phil. iii. 17.</note> but rather urge you to <hi>walk as you have him for an example,</hi> and that in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, univerſality, conſtancy, and induſtry of an <hi>inoffenſive</hi> obedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The ſincerity of that obedience conſiſts in having a <hi>Conſcience void of offence,</hi> which <hi>Conſcience</hi> is the knowledge we have of our ſelves, common with others, God,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40625:4"/>and his holy Angels: Or a concluding Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in a practical Syllogiſm, whereof Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture makes the Major Propoſition: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever obeys, or obeys not, ſhall be accordingly ſaved or damned. To which Conſcience aſſumes, by excuſing, or accuſing, that I ſo do, or do not obey; and having thus witneſſed at the Bar, it takes the Tribunal, and (ſuitably to its own Verdict) acquits or condemns, I, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutes too, as being in its own Court, Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Judge, and Executioner. And Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as it is well inſtructed, concludes rightly; or as miſinſtructed, concludes falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; or as doubtful, concludes not at all; or if probable, concludes on probable reaſons. Now the good, and erroneous Conſcience both bind; that ſimply, and this ſuppoſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, till better informed. The robbing of <hi>Baal Berith</hi> was Sacriledge with them who were perſwaded he was a God.
<note place="margin">Judg. ix. 4.</note> But the <hi>Conſcience</hi> here in the <hi>Text</hi> is a true counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part of the Divine Law which is its rule, a <hi>Zeal according to knowledge,</hi> and ſo to <hi>know the will of God, as to do it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Conſcience void of offence,</hi> or ſcandal, that loves not to give, or take it. As when we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40625:5"/>neither lay Galtraps in the way of others, to obſtruct them in their Chriſtian fight, or race; nor ſtumble at thoſe that are laid in our way by others. When evil exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or inſtruction is followed, that is a true ſcandal effectually given. When what is good, or indifferent, is miſinterpreted, or avoided, when by juſt Authority command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that is a falſe offence effectually taken. <hi>Offences</hi> may be ſometimes <hi>given</hi> where they are not <hi>taken,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. iv.</note> as in <hi>Satan</hi>'s ſeveral temptings of our Saviour; and they may be <hi>taken</hi> where they are not <hi>given:</hi> Thus <hi>Chriſt was a ſtone of offence, ſet for the falling of many in Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to <hi>have a Conſcience void of offence,</hi> is to have a right knowledge of our rule of duty, and of our ſuitable compliance with it. And that,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> In the univerſality of our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as firſt it reſpects God, who cannot properly be ſaid to be <hi>offended</hi> by us, ſince <hi>grief</hi> is no more <hi>in him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. xxvii. 4.</note> than <hi>fury</hi> is; but only by way of Analogy, or reſemblance, when we do what in us lies to provoke him, by breach of the Letter, and contempt of the penalty of his Laws, affronting his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40625:5"/>Omniſcience, his Holineſs, and his Juſtice, by ſaying <hi>the God of Jacob ſees not,</hi> or ſees not to <hi>regard:</hi> And <hi>offence toward him</hi> is <hi>avoided,</hi> by firm belief of his Attributes, and a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable <hi>ſtanding in aw</hi> of them, ſo as <hi>not to ſin</hi> againſt them. Conſidering,
<note place="margin">1 John iii. 20.</note> that <hi>if our heart condemn us, God is greater than our heart, and knoweth all things.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. iv. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>All things are naked and open before him,</hi> as the Sacrifice was, when flay'd, and chin'd down, and all its inwards expoſed to view. If Conſcience is a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Witneſſes, God is more than a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Conſciences, whom we muſt ever <hi>ſet before us,</hi> which was the mean he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed <hi>Abraham</hi> to expreſs ſincerity,
<note place="margin">Gen. xvii. 1.</note> and to attain <hi>perfection.</hi> Not that our <hi>eye-ſervice</hi> brings God before us, but finds and owns him there, becauſe every where; and every where ſuch <hi>a ſearcher of the heart,</hi> and a <hi>diſcerner</hi> and Judge <hi>of its thoughts, and intents,</hi> that with him a <hi>luſtful look is Adultery,</hi> a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious will is Murder, and a covetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Theft. <hi>He judgeth not as man judgeth.</hi> With us the mind makes not guilty, without the Act, nor the Act without the mind: But with him the conceptions of Luſt are ſin, as well as the productions, as the Child is the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40625:6"/>ſame in the Womb and at the Breaſt. It is then no advantage to us to have none conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of our Evil Acts without us, while we have a Conſcience within us; or to have no Conſcience within us, while we have a God above us. We may <hi>dig deep to hide our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel from him,</hi> but he will <hi>bring forth the thing that is hid to light.</hi> So that when we are ſate from the Juſtice of men, we are not ſecure from the Juſtice of God. <hi>He that made the eye ſhall not he ſee? He that teacheth man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſhall not he puniſh?</hi> We may <hi>eſcape the Sea and the Viper,</hi> yet we have a <hi>Nemeſis,</hi> an avenger within and without us; if not, we have one above us; <hi>He that is higher than the higheſt regards,</hi> even <hi>the moſt high,</hi> from whom there lies no appeal.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. ii. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>If one man ſin againſt another, the Judge ſhall judge him, but if a man ſin againſt the Lord, who ſhall plead for him?</hi> Treſpaſſes may be compromiſed, but not Tranſgreſſions,
<note place="margin">Job ix. 33.</note> for <hi>there is no man to lay his hand</hi> upon the Offender and the Offended, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he who is <hi>God-man, the only Mediator,</hi> undertake it; who yet will be no Umpire in our obſtinate and wilful quarrels, but for thoſe alone who endeavour to keep <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences void of offence toward him,</hi> by ſerving
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40625:6"/>him as without hypocriſie, ſo ſecondly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partiality too, <hi>reſpecting all his Precepts,</hi> not thinking our ſelves ſound, if we are ſo in any part, where the <hi>Leproſie brake out in the forehead,</hi> it rendred the whole man <hi>unclean.</hi> No duty is little where an Infinite God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; nor any ſin ſmall for which an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Chriſt did die, and Eternal flames are kindled. Though no one good Act can ſave us, yet any one evil Act may damn us. We may die of one wound as well as of <hi>Caeſars</hi> two and thirty. Nor will our good works compound for our bad, our Zeal for our Rebellion, or our Loyalty for our Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs. There is ſuch a firm League be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween all the Precepts, that the enemies to the one are enemies to the other. The whole <hi>Ten words</hi> being but one Law. He <hi>hath other Gods beſides the Lord, who makes his belly his God,</hi> by Gluttony, or by <hi>Concupiſcence which is Idolatry;</hi> he hath <hi>not kept a day to the Lord,</hi> but to his Luſt, who by <hi>long Prayers</hi> and a <hi>Faſt</hi> hath <hi>kill'd</hi> and <hi>taken poſſeſsion;</hi> hath firſt made the Widow, and then undone her, by <hi>devouring her Houſe</hi> or <hi>her Vineyard.</hi> And he hath <hi>taken the name of God in vain,</hi> who hath <hi>born falſe witneſs againſt his Neighbour.</hi> A
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40625:7"/>good Conſcience deſires <hi>in all things to live honeſtly.</hi> And our duty is then currant, when neither allay'd, nor clipp'd. Its intrinſick value conſiſts in a ſincere, the extrinſick in a uniform obedience. And this is <hi>a Conſcience void of offence toward God.</hi> And it muſt be ſo in the demonſtration of it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Towards men,</hi> towards every man: Toward (1.) Superiours; and they are firſt in the Second Table, and <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>hath ſaid they are Gods,</hi> whether the Gods of our Houſes, Parents; or of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, the Magiſtrate. And he commands us to do them homage <hi>by honour</hi> and <hi>Tribute;</hi> and he forbids us to plead Conſcience for diſobedience, when commanded to <hi>obey for Conſcience ſake.</hi> Which Conſcience, if truly tender, will be ſo to <hi>every appearance of evil,</hi> to Sedition, Schiſm, and Sacriledge, as well as to Blaſphemy, an Oath, or an Idol. Now Rebellion is commonly an Inceptor in the Family; where we are ill taught to <hi>bear the yoak in our youth,</hi> our elder years are empty of reſpect to the Doctrine of the Pulpit, and the Laws of the Throne; and then with the <hi>Fathers of our fleſh</hi> we are gradually taught to deſpiſe thoſe of our <hi>Faith,</hi> and of our <hi>Country</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:40625:7"/>too. But while we wound the honour of all, like Swords, we are inſenſible of the miſchiefs we do.
<note place="margin">Exod. iv. 16.</note> In Primitive Judaiſm <hi>Moſes</hi> was <hi>a God to Aaron,</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> was <hi>a mouth to Moſes,</hi> to plead for him who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected him: In Primitive Chriſtianity, when the Emperours were Heathens, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Legions would not be worſe, by becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rebels; but with their Swords by their ſides, received thoſe of their Executioners into their bowels, as an effect not of their Cowardize, but of their Valour; he dares do any thing, but ſin, for his Religion, who dares die for it.
<note place="margin">Luke xxii. 38.</note> In Chriſt's Retinue <hi>two Swords,</hi> when ſheathed, were <hi>enough,</hi> and one, when drawn in his defence, was too much. His <hi>Goſpel</hi> muſt not, like the <hi>Alchoran,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. xxvi. 52.</note> be propagated by Armies: Nor his Kingdom, like that of <hi>Romulus,</hi> be founded in the bloud of any but our <hi>elder Brother,</hi> that is, his own. He aſſerted the right of <hi>Caeſar</hi> by Precept, and Practice, employs his Divinity to atteſt his Loyalty,
<note place="margin">Mat. xvii. 37.</note> and <hi>out of the mouth of a Fiſh</hi> ſends the <hi>Tribute</hi> ſilver to him to whom it was <hi>ſuperſcribed,</hi> and that for <hi>himſelf and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> who did not angle for his own profit, laid no claim to the <hi>Roman-penny:</hi> We ill
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40625:8"/>requite the goodneſs of God in <hi>giving us Kings as Nurſing Fathers,</hi> when we undermine the Thrones we are by many obligations bound to ſupport. Nor matters it much whether we do it by <hi>Achitophels</hi> head, or <hi>Abſaloms</hi> hand, by <hi>Shimei</hi>'s tongue, or <hi>Sheba's</hi> trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. If the Jew was enjoyned to <hi>pray for that Land where he was Captive,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. xxix. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>ſince in the peace thereof he was to have peace:</hi> How much more are we bound to <hi>ſeek the peace</hi> of the Land of our Nativity, <hi>ſince they only can proſper that love it?</hi> We ſhould not then be like fooliſh Paſſengers in a Ship, who rip up the Planks of the Veſſel, wherein they are embarked, to build their own Cabins. Sure I am, Chriſt never furniſhed us with the Doctrine of <hi>ſpeaking evil of Dignities,</hi> nor true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity with the uſe. St. <hi>Paul</hi> retracts the raſh expreſſion of <hi>Whited Wall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts xxiii. 3, &amp;c.</note> uſed to a <hi>Judge,</hi> though an unjuſt one, and that with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, and calls it his <hi>ſin,</hi> though his <hi>ſin of Ignorance:</hi> While <hi>our hearts</hi> never <hi>ſmite us</hi> for the wounds we give the <hi>Royal Robe,</hi> by the ill language we ſpeak, or hear, when the reputations of our Superiours are evapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in the ſmoak of a Coffee-houſe, and all our Allegiance lies drown'd, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40625:8"/>in Rheum, and <hi>Lethe;</hi> we muſt have a toleration for ill opinions, and ill manners too: And our Laws, like thoſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Solon</hi> to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> muſt be adapted <hi>to the hardneſs of our hearts;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. xix. 8.</note> while a War, a Plague, and a Fire have ruin'd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but reformed none: Nay,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.5.</note> our <hi>revoltings</hi> have increaſed with God's <hi>ſmitings;</hi> like the high attainers of our Age, we are above all Ordinances only by being againſt them: Of which <hi>Ordinances the powers that be</hi> are one. Our Remedy lies in the ſtrengthening the hands of our Superiours, by ſubjection to them, and love to one another, that ſince God hath <hi>given us Judges, as at the firſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">26.</note> 
                  <hi>and Counſellours as at the beginning,</hi> it may appear that with our Government we have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of our Loyalty too. And this we ſhall do, if we <hi>keep our Conſciences</hi> and our <hi>Converſations void of offence</hi> toward our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours. And</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Toward our Equals, and that in things Civil and Religious; in their concerns as Men, and as Chriſtians. Not invading their property by fraud or violence. The truly Conſciencious perſon ſhuns every diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt Act, not ſo much for the ſake of his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40625:9"/>Reputation, as his Peace; Every black <hi>mote</hi> is to him, as to a tender eye, his grief, as well as his blemiſh. He dares not wound his Soul to ſave his Eſtate, or his Life; as knowing that God hates the profitable, as well as the pious fraud, and that light gains ill got make the Conſcience more heavy than the Purſe. When good <hi>plain Jacob</hi> ſaw the <hi>Money returned with the Corn in his Son's Sacks,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. xlii. 25, &amp;c.</note> he orders them to <hi>take double money</hi> with them in their ſecond Journey, for <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure,</hi> ſays he, <hi>it was an overſight:</hi> He would not purchaſe his food too cheap, leſt he ſhould buy repentance too dear, and by ſuch an act of Injuſtice turn <hi>his bread</hi> into <hi>gravel:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. xx. 17.</note> And he is an <hi>Iſraelite indeed</hi> who is thus <hi>without guile,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John i, 47.</note> ſuch a <hi>Nathanael</hi> who <hi>is come home to Chriſt,</hi> one of whoſe Laws it is, that <hi>whatſoever we would that men ſhould do unto us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. vii. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>we ſhould do ſo unto them.</hi> I know a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian muſt do more than this, but he is no Chriſtian who doth leſs. Our <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> muſt <hi>exceed the righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. v. 20.</note> it muſt flow from a better Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and ſpring of Grace; have a larger current in our Converſation with all men, not thoſe of our own Sect only; and empty
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40625:9"/>it ſelf into a deeper Sea, God's Glory, not our own. Let <hi>us walk according to this rule in all ſimplicity and ſincerity,</hi> and then let others call it <hi>Morality,</hi> and think they can be Saints without it; whilſt Chriſt commands it, and Chriſtians practiſe it, we will call it Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, a <hi>Conſcience avoiding offence toward men</hi> in their Civil concerns. And let be ſo in (2.) their Sacred concerns too. Let us not miſguide the ignorant and ductile by <hi>falſe fires,</hi> as Thieves draw Travellers into dark Woods with a deſign to rob them. Let us <hi>not ſuffer Sin to reſt upon them,</hi> but <hi>rebuke them with a ſpirit of meekneſs,</hi> and <hi>inſtruct them with a ſpirit of wiſdom,</hi> as <hi>men of feeding lips and healing tongues.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. iv. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>Let no corrupt communication proceed out of our mouths,</hi> which is as offenſive to chaſte ears, as a ſtinking breath from rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Lungs is to the Noſtrils. Let us <hi>not judge the ſtrong, nor deſpiſe the weak,</hi> but think can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly of all, and act charitably towards all, and where we lawfully may,
<note place="margin">Phil. iv. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>let our moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be known unto all men:</hi> As tender and teeming Mothers forbear what their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs would bear for their burthens ſake. Temperance is not the want, but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of Appetite, the reſtraint of a lawful
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40625:10"/>Luſt: But <hi>Brotherly-kindneſs</hi> conſiders not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>what is lawful,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. v. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>but what is expedient alſo.</hi> St.
<note place="margin">Acts xvi. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> who very well <hi>knew that neither Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion availeth any thing, nor uncircumciſion, circumciſed Timothy</hi> to comply with the <hi>Jews,</hi> but would not <hi>circumciſe Titus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. ii. 3.</note> that he might gratifie the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> It is an unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian uſe of our Chriſtian liberty to <hi>offend</hi> the Magiſtrate in forbearing what we may do, or our Brother, in doing what we may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear. This, if ingenuouſly obſerved, would keep the peace in the great world without us, and in the little world within us too: For this is the <hi>juſtice of a good Conſcience</hi> that <hi>gives to every one his due,</hi> and to every one in his order: Firſt, <hi>Glory to God on high,</hi> and then on earth <hi>peace and good will toward men:</hi> For as we are not to diſpleaſe God to pleaſe our Prince, nor to diſpleaſe our Prince to pleaſe our Fellow-ſubjects; ſo neither are we to diſpleaſe our fellow-ſubjects to pleaſe our ſelves. Where the way is one, we can fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low both, <hi>Fear God, and the King:</hi> But where they part, we ſhew by our attendance, to which we retain. We <hi>cannot ſerve two Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<note place="margin">Dan. iii.</note> his Servants we are whom we obey.</hi> This cauſed the <hi>three Children to chuſe affliction rather
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40625:10"/>than ſin,</hi> and to deem <hi>a Furnace ſeven times heated</hi> cooler than <hi>Hell.</hi> But (God be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) this is not our caſe, and I hope will never be. We have <hi>no Statutes of Omri,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Micah vi. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>no manners of the houſe of Ahab</hi> to obey, but ſuch a Government as, be the times never ſo bad, we may be as good as we will in them; and that ſafely too, we are not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>to praiſe God in the fire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. xii. 1.</note> or to <hi>offer up our bodies as any other than a living ſacrifice</hi> to him: And are ſo far from <hi>ſuffering for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake,</hi> that we are not ſo much as <hi>buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feted for our faults:</hi> But can break the Laws pretendedly with as good a Conſcience as others can really keep them. But God, who preſcribes the Order, preſcribes the Union too; we muſt <hi>provide things honeſt in the ſight of both God, and man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. viii. 21.</note> For though Loyalty is no more founded in Grace than Dominion is, a <hi>Nero</hi> muſt be obeyed as well as a <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. xiii. 1, &amp;c.</note> and there may be as good Subjects in <hi>Turky,</hi> as in <hi>England,</hi> if not better; and an <hi>Ariſtides</hi> may be as juſt as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> yet he is no good Chriſtian who is a Rebel, or a Cheat: <hi>Chriſt</hi> will not be <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> to them who will have none of their own. His <hi>Kingdom</hi> conſiſts not in <hi>Carnal Wiſdom,</hi> or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40625:11"/>weapons, but in <hi>Love, Joy, and Peace;</hi> that peace which is both our duty, and our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and both in the Text. <hi>To have a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence void of offence toward God, and toward men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That which ſpeaks the conſtancy of duty, is that it muſt be <hi>always</hi> the ſame in all conditions, places, and times. We are to be chaſte with <hi>Joſeph,</hi> in the <hi>Palace,</hi> as well as the <hi>Priſon;</hi> within the <hi>Curtains of our bed,</hi> as thoſe of <hi>the Tabernacle.</hi> To be ſober among the Vines, and temperate at a loaded Table; to pray for <hi>the King</hi> as heartily in our <hi>Cloſets,</hi> as in his <hi>Chappel;</hi> and no more to <hi>curſe him in our Bed-chamber,</hi> than we would in his own. To be true to every truſt of the dead, as of the living; and not, as too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny among us, who are ſo unlike to God, and ſo like the Devil, that they are moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe to all that put confidence in them: Whereas an inoffenſive Conſcience ſets <hi>God</hi> and man <hi>before its eyes,</hi> and is the ſame to thoſe that may be abſent, as toward him that cannot; and that in all Conditions, <hi>when he hides his face</hi> as when <hi>he ſhines on our Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle.</hi> Its Piety is not ſtrong only when we are weak, and then languiſhing when we recover: Is not puffed up by proſperity, nor
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40625:11"/>caſt down by adverſity, as Boats that riſe with the Floud, and ſink with the Ebb. Its mouth is not full of <hi>murmuring</hi> whe uempty of bread,
<note place="margin">Phil. iv. 11.</note> but <hi>in all eſtates hath learned to be content.</hi> Can tend on the <hi>Ark</hi> when its <hi>Manna</hi> is gone, and nothing left but the <hi>Rod,</hi> and the <hi>Law,</hi> when baniſhed, as well as when it gratifies the <hi>fleſh-hook:</hi> Can be devout at <hi>Meſech</hi> and <hi>Kedar,</hi> as in the <hi>goings,</hi> and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Proceſſion of the <hi>Sanctuary.</hi> Good <hi>Barzillai</hi> was as faithful a Subject to <hi>David,</hi> when <hi>hunted on the Mountains,</hi> as when <hi>he went to be Crown'd at Hebron.</hi> A good Conſcience neither flatters the rich, nor oppreſſeth the poor; takes not the opportunity of a Friend's diſtreſs to inſult, or to betray; to <hi>ſtand aloof from the ſore,</hi> or only <hi>to pour Vinegar into it</hi> by ſharp upbraidings, or uncharitable conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; but where it cannot be a <hi>Shield</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a wound, is ever ready with <hi>Balm</hi> to heal it; not trampling on a Proſtrate, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Friend, or Enemy, but is equally prompt <hi>to do good,</hi> and to <hi>forgive evil.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">James i. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Pure and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed Religion,</hi> (the Religion of a Conſcience ſo qualified too) <hi>viſits the Fatherleſs and the Widow,</hi> with a <hi>viſit</hi> like that of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Luke i. 68.</note> 
                  <hi>viſits to redeem,</hi> and as the ſame Chriſt too, <hi>keeps it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:40625:12"/>ſelf unſpotted of the world.</hi> It throws no dirt, (and 'tis hard to do it with clean hands) nor doth any thrown at it ſtick on it, but is ſoon wiped off by undiſturbed Innocence. And this, all this is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> and laſtly, The whole employ of a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> as wherein it doth <hi>exerciſe it ſelf,</hi> (as the word ſignifies) prepares for the Combat, bends all its wit and force to it; is</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Diligent</hi> to the utmoſt of its power, <hi>ſtriving to excell</hi> others, and our ſelves. That <hi>thoſe things be in us and abound. If it be poſsible, and as much as in us lies to have peace with God and man, with all men.</hi> And this is more than a meer bending our tongues and wits to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and righteouſneſs; not a ſpeaking great things, but living them.. And though God ſometimes takes the will for the deed, it is there only <hi>where there is no ability to perform:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. viii. 12.</note> Thus <hi>Love</hi> may <hi>fulfil the whole Law</hi> in a hearty diſpoſition to all obedience where the Act is not feazible. <hi>Davids deſire to keep Gods Commandments,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. cxix. 4, 5.</note> goes for the deed; 'twas <hi>exerciſe</hi> when he did but <hi>ſtrive in Prayer</hi> after that perfection, which is not here attainable: Yet a meer preſent wiſhing we might do
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40625:12"/>God's will can no more ſecure us from Hell, than a future wiſhing we had done it can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us out of it. It is not <hi>a ſetting our faces toward Zion</hi> that will bring us thither, when like Weathercocks, the next wind of a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, alters our aſpect, and we are ſtill where we were.
<note place="margin">Mat. xxv. 15, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Two Talents</hi> improved to <hi>four</hi> have in Heaven a proportionable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, with the <hi>five</hi> that were <hi>made ten:</hi> But the lazy Well-willers <hi>Talent</hi> that <hi>ruſted in the Napkin</hi> had that <hi>ruſt</hi> as a <hi>ſwift witneſs againſt him,</hi> before that God who expects <hi>his own with uſury.</hi> We have the knowledge <hi>of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> and <hi>they are not grievous.</hi> The Dictates of his Spirit, the Aſſiſtances of our own Conſciences, the Examples of his Son and Servants, the Encouragement of all his Promiſes, which makes our <hi>ſervice</hi> as <hi>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> as it is <hi>reaſonable:</hi> And if herewith we faithfully do what we can, he will merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accept of what we do. And herein we muſt be, as diligent, ſo,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Prudent too, to <hi>ſtrive lawfully,</hi> as well as <hi>earneſtly;</hi> to have light with our heat; and that light is, in the eſſentials of Religion, the Word of God, and we are not to vary from the <hi>Pattern in the Mount.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40625:13"/>To the Law and to the Teſtimony,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. viii. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>if they ſpeak not according to this, it is becauſe there is no truth in them.</hi> They oblige our Faith in all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our ſeveral Creeds,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. i. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>thoſe forms of ſound words</hi> founded in Scripture. Our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in worſhipping God by Prayer, and Praiſe, by hearing, and receiving his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, revering his Name, avoiding Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm, Atheiſm, Idolatry, Blaſphemy, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring our Superiours, not invading the Life, Chaſtity, Eſtate, or Reputation of our Neighbour: Which Laws are a Moral and perpetual rule to all our Intentions, Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and Actions, and with theſe neither men nor our own Conſciences can diſpenſe: And our trial at the laſt day will be not meerly by our Conſciences, but as they have been guided by that Word. Since Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, like Fame, may be as tenacious of a lie as of a truth, may condemn where God acquits, or acquit where God condemns. He muſt touch the Needle to make it point right, which elſe will vary (as we know Conſcience hath done) to all the Points in the Compaſs. We rightly ſet our Watches by the Dial, when we are aſſured the Dial is well ſet by the Sun.</p>
               <p>In things Civil, the rule is right Reaſon; we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40625:13"/>expect not a Law out of Scripture for every minute action of Life. We try a Circle not by a Square, but by a Compaſs. The Law of the Land, where it ſpeaks, is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Conſcience which ought to guide us in all things that are not apparently oppoſite to the Divine Law. The Church is a <hi>Vineyard,</hi> and is in the State, as in it's <hi>Fence,</hi> without which it would not be long a <hi>Vineyard.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. i. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſrael</hi> was <hi>Loammi,</hi> that is, not <hi>a People,</hi> when <hi>without the true God, a teaching Prieſt, and Law, when the Pillars are diſſolved the People melt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chron. xv. 3.</note> By un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining our Superiours we Sap our own foundations; and while we pluck flowers from the Crown to weave Garlands for our ſelves, the ſucceſs is to ſee both droop, and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together. Did we rightly underſtand things, we ſhould acknowledge it our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be ſubject, the very worſt of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being better than none. Law is the Mound of Property, and without that enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, every man would turn all his Luſts, like Beaſts without ſtint, into the Common. Now the Law is but a dead letter, it's life is it's execution, and it's beſt execution is in our active obedience. It is not indifferent to the Law, or the Lawgiver, whether we do
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40625:14"/>or ſuffer; as it is in By-laws of Corporations whether we fine or ſerve. Juſtice would be all Sword, if it did not only conſiſt in the mulcting or puniſhing our Perſons, or our Purſes. It is from our corruptions that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Statutes are inflicted as well as enacted. Would we <hi>be a Law to our ſelves,</hi> we ſhould not need ſo many from our Superiours. It is then as imprudent as it is ungrateful, like <hi>Sons of Belial,</hi> to ſhake off that eaſie yoak, that protects where it reſtrains, and by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us in order, keeps us in ſafety too. Let the <hi>Law</hi> of the Land ſubdue that of <hi>our Luſts;</hi> Let us <hi>ſtudy to be quiet,</hi> and <hi>to do our own buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> And leaving the Steerage of the Veſſel to thoſe that ſit at the Helm, let us keep our own Cabins, and there ſtrengthen, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage our Pilots by our Devotion, and by our Subjection.</p>
               <p>In things indifferent let us walk by the rule of Charity, but of Charity firſt to the Church our <hi>Mother,</hi> and as we owe to her our better birth, ſo let us pay her our better <hi>Honour.</hi> Her love firſt deſcended on us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ours could aſcend to her, and now we are able, let ours aſcend to her, before it ſpread to the Brethren; 'tis the Method and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40625:14"/>order of Grace as well as of Nature. In purſuance of which, let us not diſpute her Wiſdom, or her Authority in confining our practice in what makes for <hi>Decency, or Order,</hi> whereof ſhe is certainly a more competent Judge than her Children: In God's name, let us <hi>ſearch the Scriptures</hi> for every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Worſhip, but then let us not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, we find not this thing commanded there, therefore we dare not do it; but rather, we find not this thing there forbid, therefore we may do it;
<note place="margin">Rom. iv. 15.</note> for <hi>where there is no Law there is no tranſgreſsion:</hi> If we doubt, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Authority ſuperſedes the doubt. But while we peremptorily avoid what is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, we meet that Judaiſm we pretend to run from; and are <hi>too ſuperſtitious</hi> whilſt we would not be at all ſo. Nay, we loſe that liberty whereof we are ſo tender, as by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſed to one ſide, and that againſt the Powers that are ſet over us, we are eaſily drawn away by thoſe who have no right to guide us, but are reſtiff and head-ſtrong to thoſe that have a right to our obedience; like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched Gallants, who value their Curtizan above their Chirurgion, and will give more to get a Diſeaſe than to have it cured. Where
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40625:15"/>the Word is ſilent, we have our <hi>Liberty,</hi> but let us <hi>not uſe it for any occaſion of the ſleſh.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. ii. 16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Primitive Chriſtians when confined to <hi>a few things</hi> made <hi>neceſſary</hi> by the Precept, and not ſo in themſelves, ſuch as <hi>abſtinence from things ſtrangled,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts xv. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>and from bloud,</hi> are ſaid to <hi>rejoice for the Conſolation.</hi> And ſo did our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors when reform'd from that Worſhip which was become all husk, and ſhell, and rind; yet thought not themſelves obliged to ſtrip off all the Leaves from Chriſt's Vine, as if they injured thoſe Grapes which they overſhadowed; whoſe moderation let us imitate, <hi>following after the things which make for peace.</hi> And nothing makes more for it than our <hi>hearing the Inſtructions of our Civil Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. i. 8.</note> and not <hi>forſaking the Law of</hi> the Church <hi>our Mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here, were the Orator as good as the Cauſe, I ſhould hope, with as much ſucceſs as willingneſs, to plead for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Doctrine and Diſcipline are a perfect Comment on this <hi>Text, a giving to God and Caeſar their due;</hi> receiving as a rule of faith all the Articles of the Three Creeds, preſerving to God his Worſhip entire, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the rivallings of Saints, or Angels, or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40625:15"/>
                  <hi>the likeneſs of any thing above or below.</hi> Not invading or depreſſing the Offices of Chriſt by <hi>Lording it over his Heritage,</hi> or derogating from his Satisfaction, or Interceſſion, by owning any other Purgatory but that of his ſufferings in this world, to ſecure us from thoſe of the world to come. And therefore teaching us <hi>that no man can</hi> by Maſſes, Oblations, Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, or works of Supererogation <hi>redeem his Brother, or pay to God a ranſom for him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. xlix. 7.</note> And that the all-ſufficient merits of Chriſt need not be Imp'd by ours, or thoſe of <hi>men ſubject to like paſsions with our ſelves.</hi> And therefore we look on Heaven not as <hi>wages,</hi> but as <hi>gift,</hi> yet are <hi>careful to maintain good works,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. vi. 23.</note> as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to <hi>ſalvation,</hi> which is that <hi>Penny</hi> that is <hi>paid</hi> to none but thoſe that <hi>labour:</hi> But when we have <hi>ſow'd in righteouſneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. x. 12.</note> we hope <hi>to reap in mercy.</hi> We own <hi>but one Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and us;</hi> Nor can we think our bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Moſes</hi> needs any <hi>Aaron</hi> or <hi>Hur to ſupport his hands,</hi> in that <hi>Mount</hi> above, whilſt he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedes for his Church that is militant here below. And therefore as we adore not what is left of the Saints here, ſo we ſue not to what is <hi>aſcended</hi> of them <hi>on high.</hi> Nor dare we give that worſhip to a dead <hi>Barnabas</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40625:16"/>
                  <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts xiv. 11.</note> which they refuſed when living. How can we <hi>call on them in whom we have not believed?</hi> We dare not vacate the Prophetical Office of Chriſt, by <hi>teaching for Doctrines the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men.</hi> We own ſuch Traditions, as <hi>can prove their Pedigree</hi> to be truly ancient, not repugnant to Scripture, and to conſiſt with <hi>Decency and Order.</hi> And that every National Church hath power to determine practice in things indifferent, and to bind <hi>to obedience for Conſcience ſake,</hi> Conſcience of that duty that is owing to the fifth Commandment; But we <hi>follow not cunningly deviſed fables,</hi> while <hi>we have a more ſure word of Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</hi> We receive the Sacraments in their due number, and order, and by the Font we paſs to the Altar, for ſo we can call it, as its <hi>ſhew-bread is a Commemorative Sacrifice,</hi> tendered not to God for us, but by him to us; and as at it we offer up our ſelves to him <hi>once offered up for us</hi> in the Chriſtian <hi>Sacrifices of a broken heart,</hi> a thankful tongue, a charitable hand, and an holy life.</p>
               <p>We have a Liturgy in a <hi>known tongue,</hi> that ſo we may <hi>pray with the underſtanding,</hi> and know <hi>to what we ſay Amen.</hi> And if we <hi>pray</hi> not <hi>with the ſpirit too</hi> (I mean not that of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40625:16"/>
                  <hi>gift of Tongues,</hi> but) <hi>of prayer and ſupplication,</hi> both Gods, and our own, it is our own fault that moſt excellent expreſſions are not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with ſuitable affections. If our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer be a dead Letter, our hearts make it ſo; for no Cloaths will warm the dead: And without the <hi>pouring out of the heart,</hi> the pouring out of words, extempore, or premeditated, is <hi>but the ſacrifice of fools,</hi> and that whether a <hi>Phariſee</hi> lengthen, or <hi>Beads</hi> number it. And as we have the ſame ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite for our <hi>daily bread,</hi> we can in the ſame words beg it of him, who gives it, and hath given us a form wherein to ask it.</p>
               <p>And as our Church is conſcienciouſly care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>to avoid all offence toward God,</hi> ſo is ſhe no leſs <hi>toward men.</hi> And although ground be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Milſtones of the Papiſt, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring her as Schiſmatical, and the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick condemning her as Papiſtical, yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims the diſloyal principles, and practices of both the Conclave and the Claſſes. Not affecting the title of curſed <hi>Cham,</hi> as he who will be called <hi>a ſervant of ſervants,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. ix. 29.</note> yet like <hi>ſervants on horſe-back</hi> bring <hi>Princes to his foot, and exalts himſelf above all that are called Gods.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl x. 7.</note> And if any pretending Proteſtants among us
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40625:17"/>have done <hi>otherwiſe, they went out from us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not of us.</hi> We are taught not to hew out Reformation by the Sword, whoſe mouth is an ill Advocate for the truth. It is uſually drawn in the quarrel of a Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizan, but not of a chaſte Wife. If any thing be amiſs, we expect the amendment from thoſe Powers that did at firſt orderly and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively reform us, whoſe Supremacy in all Cauſes Civil and Eccleſiaſtical we humbly recognize, as excluſive of all Foreign Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, without giving them what they claim not, the Adminiſtration of Gods Word and Sacraments. And as our Church as a tender Mother denies not pardon to her Children even for wilful ſins, committed after Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm; ſo like a prudent Mother, ſhe <hi>heals</hi> not their <hi>hurts ſlightly,</hi> by the palliate cures of eaſie Confeſſion, and haſty Abſolutions, on meer Attrition, or pecuniary Commutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or ſlight corporal Penances. She ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves of no <hi>ſorrow</hi> but that <hi>godly</hi> one that <hi>worketh repentance never to be repented of:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. vii. 10.</note> Such tears as quench the fire of Luſt, and ſuch a Reformation as withdraws the fuel. We are ſo taught by her the tremendous myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Predeſtination, and Election, as to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40625:17"/>ſteer evenly between the two equally dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous rocks of Preſumption and Deſpair. She impoſeth not on her Miniſters, or others, the <hi>hard</hi> yoak of Celibacy or ſingle life, but teacheth them, and by them,
<note place="margin">Heb. xiii. 4.</note> that <hi>Marriage is honourable among all, and the bed undefiled</hi> is true Chaſtity. That Continency is not, as Faith, Hope, Charity, Repentance, and Fear, common to all Chriſtians, but pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to ſome, and is a gift that may be denied to them <hi>that ask it in Prayer,</hi> ſince where it is not, God hath by Matrimony provided a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. Nor doth ſhe bind any to Poverty, and a Mendicant ſtate,
<note place="margin">Prov. xxx. 8.</note> which wiſe <hi>Agur</hi> did deprecate; as if that could be a bleſſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, which was a curſe under the Law, to <hi>ſerve in the want of all things.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deu. xxviii. 48.</note> She obligeth not by any Vows,
<note place="margin">Num. xxx. 7.</note> but what are free, deliberate in things poſſible, and lawful, and with conſent of Superiours. She de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives us not of half our Legacy in the New Teſtament of our dying Saviour, by enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining us at a dry Communion, and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us the <hi>Cup of bleſsing.</hi> Nor doth ſhe rob us of all our reaſon, and the better half of our ſenſes by the incredible Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, that pregnant Mother
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40625:18"/>of Errors, that would perſwade us that is <hi>fleſh,</hi> which we <hi>ſee, taſte,</hi> and <hi>feel</hi> is a Wafer. That there are but the accidents of Bread, ſhape, and colour, and accidents without a ſubject;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. xi. 26.</note> whereas it is truly called <hi>bread</hi> as <hi>before,</hi> ſo <hi>after</hi> the <hi>Conſecration.</hi> That with the ſame mouth we can make, and eat our God. Firſt, <hi>change his glorious body into the likeneſs of our ſinful ones,</hi> and then <hi>caſt him out into the viler draught.</hi> That every loaf and bit ſhall be the whole man, and at the ſame time in ſo many ſeveral places: But it is not fleſh and bloud,
<note place="margin">Mat. v. 6.</note> but <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> that we <hi>hunger and thirſt after,</hi> and have the bleſſing of ſatisfaction in. Yet we receive that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not as a meer badge of our Profeſſion but as a ſign and ſeal of God's mercy to us, and of his grace thereby working in us, which grace depends not upon the worthy or unworthy qualifications of him that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, but of them who receive that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Which while we celebrate in <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</hi> of an abſent <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we yet own a <hi>real preſence</hi> of him who is every where: While we pray that we may ſo <hi>eat and drink, that our bodies may be cleanſed by his body, and our ſouls waſhed by his moſt precious bloud.</hi> And the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40625:18"/>whole office performed with as much reſpect as is required, or was practiſed by the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, though we proceed not to a <hi>preſerving, enſhrining, proceſsion</hi> with, and <hi>adoration</hi> of the <hi>Hoſt,</hi> or any other <hi>elevation,</hi> but that of the <hi>lifting up of our hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo let us ever <hi>lift them up</hi> in thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to that God, who hath <hi>called us out of darkneſs into his marvelous light,</hi> in a Church and under a Government old as Chriſtianity it ſelf, <hi>whoſe gray hairs are its Crown,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. xvi. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>as found in a way of righteouſneſs.</hi> It is <hi>called Hereſie</hi> and Novelty, yet it is the <hi>good old way,</hi> wherein we <hi>worſhip the God of our Fathers;</hi> a <hi>righteous,</hi> though a <hi>dolorous way,</hi> as by which the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and one of the beſt of Kings walked to their Croſs: In this Profeſſion died the true <hi>Defender of the</hi> Church in its ancient <hi>Faith,</hi> and fruitions; equally abhorring <hi>Sacriledge</hi> and <hi>Apoſtacy:</hi> Who by no Arts or force could be brought to ſubject her to parity or poverty, to gratifie thoſe who would have her go as <hi>naked out of the world,</hi> as ſhe <hi>came into it.</hi> He took care not to have his <hi>neſt fired by a coal ſnatched from God's Altar,</hi> earneſtly praying that neither he, nor his might ever be acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to it. And (God be thanked) he hath been
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:40625:19"/>hitherto <hi>heard in what he deſired.</hi> Thus he was the <hi>moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> by a better title than that to <hi>France,</hi> as purchaſed, not by his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects blood, but by his own: He was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to exchange a <hi>Crown of Gold</hi> for a <hi>Crown of Thorns,</hi> and for which he now wears a <hi>Crown of Glory.</hi> And may that Religion which ſuch a <hi>Saviour</hi> founded in, and ſuch a <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign</hi> ſealed with his bloud, be our Religion for ever.</p>
               <closer>Amen and Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Application to the Occaſion.</head>
               <p>AND now it is time to give you an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a fit Servant and Subject to ſuch a Chriſt, and ſuch a King: And you have one before you, that of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Friend. He <hi>kept a Conſcience void of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence toward God and toward man.</hi> To trace him as high as we can, he was of a generous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and therein the obedient Son of an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging Father, and from thence he was the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Servant of a good Maſter, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the kind Maſter of many Servants. But what is here moſt proper to conſider him in, is his better <hi>Profeſsion,</hi> that of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that of a <hi>Proteſtant:</hi> And herein he was a ſteady Profeſſor, too well ballaſted to be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40625:19"/>
                  <hi>carried about by every (by any) wind of Doctrine,</hi> whether it blew from <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Geneva.</hi> He lived to ſee Religion in its ſplendour, and its eclipſe, and he equally loved it in both condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or if there was any difference, he exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the latter.</p>
               <p>When thoſe Vipers, who ſuck'd the breaſts of the Church, were ready to tear out her bowels, ſhe took ſanctuary in his houſe, and there frequently dealt out her <hi>bread of life</hi> in the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Sacrament,</hi> by many of her <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> to many of her <hi>Children.</hi> There afflicted Loyalty had wherewithal to <hi>content it,</hi> for it had <hi>food, and raiment</hi> from thence. How <hi>many of the Lords Prophet</hi> did this good <hi>Obadiah</hi> refreſh with ſomething better than <hi>bread and water?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Kings xviii. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He was for many years very uſeful to this Pariſh, wherein there was nothing that he did diſreliſh more than diſhoneſty: He had a clear head to diſcern it, and a clean heart to abhor it. When his example could not allure men to a ſincere, his ſtrict juſtice would aw them into an outward honeſty. Among thoſe loſſes we ſuſtain'd by the late dreadful ſire, it was none of the leaſt that it parted him and us; yet when he <hi>went from us</hi> he ſeemed ſtill <hi>to be of us.</hi> We had (as of a ſetting Sun) ſomewhat of his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40625:20"/>head to enlighten us, and of his heart to warm us. And how open was his hand to repair this Church, when no longer his Church? So that ſhould I be ſilent,
<note place="margin">Hab. ii. 11.</note> the <hi>ſtone in the wall, and the beam out of the timber</hi> would charge me with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude: Theſe ſpeak his Epitaph, while the whole Fabrick is his Monument. There are other Charities too, wherein I could be loud with a <hi>zeal for him according to knowledge,</hi> my own knowledge; but that he, who in all his good deeds ſought God's glory, and not his own, hath thereby enjoyn'd me ſilence. It was enough for him to do them, and then to leave it to God to reward them; and he did them with that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, that he deem'd he did not deſerve the <hi>praiſe of men,</hi> much leſs that <hi>of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His behaviour in the Royal Society of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries (for <hi>King James</hi> who made them a Company uſed to call them <hi>his Society</hi>) was ſuch as gained him the applauſe and affections of all. They found enough, if not too much to imitate, nothing to condemn. It is not unknown to many of you that thoſe publick buildings too owe much to his Care, and Charity. He was very Inſtrumental to rear them, out of their aſhes, who is now dropp'd into his own, only with this difference, that he expects what they enjoy,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40625:20"/>to have <hi>his later ſtate made better than his former.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His laſt Scene of life was ſutable to all the reſt, a work of Charity; when haſtening to God he took the <hi>Hoſpital of St. Bartholomew</hi> in his way. Hither the unanimous votes of the Governours, the panting deſires of the Sick and Lame, with the importunate Letters of the ever Venerable Mr. <hi>Mills</hi> his Predeceſſor invited him. This good old man could not die, till ſatisfied he ſhould ſurvive himſelf in ſuch a Succeſſor; and then he ſung his <hi>Nune Dimittis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here our Friend enjoy'd, if not the moſt honourable, yet the moſt advantagious imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is, advantageous to others, not to himſelf. For he did not ſell, but <hi>give himſelf to good works.</hi> And here they had a Treaſure in a Treaſurer, <hi>a Treaſure</hi> that <hi>is</hi> indeed <hi>in heaven</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The Motto of his Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ring.</note>, no ſooner ſhew'd to them than ſnatch'd from them. The <hi>Treaſure</hi> is gone, and nothing but the <hi>earthen veſſel</hi> remains, to ſhew how poor we are; The Wife, in the loſs of a moſt affectionate Husband; the Sick, of a Compaſſionate Father; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, of a loving Brother, and my ſelf of a kind and conſtant Friend. For, give me leave to tell you, that had it not been for his and ſome others endeavours ſixteen years ago in my behalf, I had not been now here, to give him this juſt teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of my gratitude to his memory.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:40625:21"/>
               <p>And now farewel <hi>Pious Chriſtian, Loyal Subject, Faithful Friend, Juſt Steward,</hi> and <hi>Good Samarican:</hi> yet we take no entire leave of thee, we take no leave of thy <hi>memory,</hi> that <hi>of the Juſt is ever bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> The names of <hi>Mills,</hi> and <hi>Hinton</hi> can never die. We take no leave of thy life, we will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to live like thee, that we may live with thee. We take but a ſhort leave of thy body, Thou art going to the <hi>bottom of the Grave,</hi> and we are at <hi>the brink</hi> of it. We are all but <hi>awake</hi> for a while, and then we ſhall not <hi>ſleep</hi> for ever. <hi>Chriſt ſhall change our vile bodies</hi> together, with thine, and <hi>make them like to his own moſt glorious body, according to that mighty working whereby he is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf.</hi> When we ſhall hear what we hope, and believe thou haſt already heard, even that comfortable invitation, and Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Come ye bleſſed Children of my Father, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Kingdom prepared for you from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world. You have been faithful in a few things, I will make you Rulers over many things, enter into the Joy of your Lord,</hi> for which he fit us, and to which he bring us <hi>through ſanctification of the Spirit, and belief of the truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Amen and Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
